Hanoi has a bundle of places to visit: Hanoi Old Town Quarter, Hoan Kiem Lake, Temple of Literature, Ho Chi Minh Mausoleum, Vietnam Museum of Ethnology, Hoa Lo Prison, Museum, Water Puppet Theatre, Military History Museum, Fine Art Musseum, Imperial Citadel and West Lake.
Hanoi has undoubtedly one of the most diverse and unique cuisines in Asia and the world with its colorful flavors of sweet sour spicy and the crunchy texture of fresh herbs that dial down the strong flavors, creating a culinary harmony in your mouth. Top dishes that you must try as a tourist in Hanoi are beef noodle soup, vermicelli noodle with grilled pork, crab vermicelli noodle, turmeric fish with dill, Vietnamese baguette, rolled cake, sweet sticky rice, deep fried Vietnamese spring rolls, Vietnamese fresh spring rolls, and rice noodle rolls.
Hanoi street food is very diverse, delicious and healthy gastronomies in the world. The main ingredients used in Vietnamese food are rice and its derivatives, vegetables and fish sauce. There are hundreds of recipes to make Vietnamese foods but you will see these mainly features: combination with different cuisines, healthy and less fatty, very tasty with a lot of flavors, perfect combination between a lot of spices and ingredients, delicious, healthy and easy to eat, using chopsticks, community eating, hospitality, and serving foods in a tray.
Across the streets of Hanoi, one can see sidewalk cafes everywhere. But there are several streets where the entire sidewalks are occupied by coffee shops: Nguyen Du Street, Trieu Viet Vuong Street, and Nha Tho street.
The area around Hanoi – the name means ‘within the waters’, a reference to the city’s close relationship with the Song Hong, or ‘Red River’ and numerous surrounding lakes – has been the site of Vietnam’s capital, on and off, for more than two millennium. In the 3rd century BC, King Thuc Phan established the earliest Vietnamese capital at the citadel of Co Loa just north of the present-day city. More than 1,000 years later, when the Chinese were driven out and independence restored, General Ngo Quyen symbolically chose Hanoi as the site of the reborn Vietnamese nation. In 1010, the king Ly Cong Uan moved the capital from Hoa Lu to Hanoi now and named it as Thang Long. Subsequently, in 1802, the first Nguyen Emperor, Gia Long, transferred the capital to Hue – but this proved to be a short-lived move. In 1902, France established Hanoi as the capital not just of Vietnam, but of all French Indochina. In 1954, the city became the capital of the communist north. From 1968 – 1972, Hanoi was bombed several times by American and in 1976, following the defeat of the south regime; Hanoi was pro-claimed capital of the reunited Socialist Republic of Vietnam. In many ways, Hanoi remains the heart of the Vietnamese nation.
With the history of more than 100 years, Hanoi’s names had been change many time in different periods. The given name wasn’t random but it showed an important side of the city at the time. During the rule of the Chinese people, Hanoi used to be called Tong Binh District in history books from the years 454-456 under the Southern and Northern Dynasty of China. Later, Hanoi was renamed Dai La. Dai La, or Dai La citadel, formerly called the outer citadel surrounding the capital. According to ancient architecture, the capital often has three citadels including the Forbidden City where the king and royal family live, the Royal Citadel in the middle and the outer citadel Dai La. Long Do (navel of a dragon) is also a name of Hanoi, but not the official name. This name appeared from the time of Cao Bien. Legend has it that, in the year 866, when Cao Bien built Dai La, he saw a god claiming to be Long Do. Hence, the history documents often called Thang Long as Long Do. When Vietnam gained independence, Hanoi became the capital at the time of Dai Viet from the 11th century with the name of Thang Long (which means “flying dragon”), after Ly Cong Uan claimed to move the capital in 1010. Thang Long was the capital until 1397 when the capital was moved to Thanh Hoa (meaning Tay Do). Thang Long then called Dong Do. In 1408, Dai Ngu nation of father and son Ho was invaded by the Ming army and Dong Do was renamed as Dong Quan. In 1428, after Le Loi’s army liberated the country, it was renamed Dong Kinh – the Europeans transliterated into Tonkin. Under Tay Son Dynasty, as the capital is located in Phu Xuan, the capital was named Bac Thanh. In 1802, when the Nguyen Dynasty moved the new capital to Hue, it was renamed, Thang Long, but this time, the word “Long” represents prosperity, rather than the dragon, for the reason that the dragon is a symbol of the king, and the king is not here, it is not allowed to use the word “Long” as a meaning of “dragon”. Then King Gia Long ordered to tear down the old citadel because the capital was not in Thang Long and Thang Long citadel was too wide. In 1831, King Minh Mang founded Ha Noi province. When Vietnam interacted with the West, Sino-Vietnamese name of Hanoi was Dong Kinh, written into Tonkin and Europeans were commonly used. In 1873, the French began to strike Hanoi and 10 years later, they dominated the entire nation. Since 1887, Hanoi became the capital of Indochina belonging to French. In 1940, the city was invaded by Japanese fascists and in 1945 Hanoi was liberated and was the place located the department of the Government of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam. From 1946 to 1954, Hanoi was in a fierce battleground between Vietnamese army and the French military. After being liberated on October 10, 1954, Hanoi became the capital of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam. During the Vietnam War, the traffic construction of Hanoi such as bridges and railway were destroyed by bombs but immediately corrected. During this time, Hanoi was hailed as “Capital of human dignity”. Hanoi became the capital of the whole Vietnam after the unification of the north and south after July 2, 1976. Hanoi has many other informal names, appearing mainly in poetry and folklore: Trang An or Truong An (taken from the name of the Chinese capital under Han and Tang dynasties); Phung Thanh or Phuong Thanh; Long Thanh, Long Bien, Ke Cho (in the folk); Thuong Kinh, Kinh Ky, Ha Thanh, Hoang Dieu, shortly after the August Revolution – 1945, sometimes in the newspapers of Vietnam used this name to refer to Hanoi.
Hanoi belongs to Red River Delta geography zone. The city is located from 20°53' to 21°23' north latitude and from 105°44' to 106°02' east longitude. The capital shares borders with Thai Nguyen and Vinh Phuc in the north, Ha Nam and Hoa Binh in the south, Bac Giang, Hung Yen and Bac Ninh in the east, and Hoa Binh and Phu Tho in the west. After the administrative boundaries expansion on August 2008, the city has the total area of 3323.6 km2 (according to the statistics in 2012 of General Statistics Office of Vietnam). Hanoi is located in both sides of the Red River, but mainly focuses on the right bank.
The city has four extreme points, which are: the North Pole (Bac Son Commune, Soc Son District), the West Pole (Thuan My Commune, Ba Vi District), the South Pole: Huong Son Commune, My Duc District), the East Pole (Le Chi Commune, Gia Lam District).
Hanoi topography is gradually lower from the north to the south and from the west to the east with the average elevation of 5 – 20 meters above the sea level. Hanoi has two main terrains including plains and hills. Plain areas are mainly located in the old area of Hanoi and some eastern districts of old Ha Tay province. These areas are situated on the right bank of the Black River and two sides of the Red River. Plains account for three fourth of the natural area of Hanoi.  Besides, the hilly terrain belongs to some provinces including Soc Son, Ba Vi, Quoc Oai, and My Duc. Some high hills of the city  are Ba Vi (1281m), Gia De (707m), Chan Chim (462m), Thanh Lanh (427m), Thien Tru (378m), Ba Tuong (334m), Sc Son (308m), Nui Boc (245m), Duc Linh (294m) and so on.
Hanoi weather is fairly typical for the general climate in the north of Vietnam. Hanoi climate is characterized by the tropical monsoon climate with hot and rainy summers and cold and dry winters.  Located in the Tropic, Hanoi receives the large amount of solar radiation all around year with the high temperature. The average amount of total radiation each year in Hanoi is 122.8 kcal/cm2. The average temperature of air is 23.6ºC per year. Due to the influence of sea, the land has the large humidity and rainfall. The average humidity is 79% while the average annual rainfall is 1800 mm. There are about 114 rainy days each year in the capital.
Weather in Hanoi has two distinct seasons. Dry and hot seasons last from May to September. The average temperature in this season is 29.2ºC. Winter seasons last from November to March. The average temperature of Hanoi winter is 15.2 ºC. Between these two seasons, there is a transition period (in April and October); therefore, Hanoi has 4 seasons in one year. The changes in weather of four seasons make Hanoi having its own beauty in each season. The most suitable time to travel in Hanoi is in spring. Besides, the topography of old Ha Tay has its own features which form the climatic sub-regions including mountains, hills and plains. However, in general, the differences in weather and temperature among regions in Hanoi are not very large.
Hanoi's area is 3323.6 sq. km.
Hanoi has 10 districts: Hoan Kiem, Ba Dinh, Dong Da, Hai Ba Trung, Hoang Mai, Tay Ho, Thanh Xuan, Cau Giay, Long Bien, and Ha Dong.
Hanoi is located next to two big rivers which are the Black River and the Red River. The Red River is the main river of the city. The length of Red River flowing through Hanoi is 163 km, which accounts for one third of the length of the river in Vietnam. The Black River is the boundary between Hanoi and Phu Tho. Apart from these two rives, Hanoi also has some smaller rivers flowing in the inner city such as Day River, Duong River, Cau River and Ca Lo River, etc. Some other rivers have an important role in the drainage of Hanoi such as To Lich River, Kim Nguu River. Hanoi also has a plenty of lakes, which are remnants of the ancient rivers. In the inner city, West Lake has the largest area, about 500 hectares. West Lake plays an important role in the urban landscape of the city. Besides, Hoan Kiem Lake or Guom Lake is also a large lake in Hanoi. Hoan Kiem Lake is situated in the historical and busiest center of the city. In addition, there are many other lakes including Truc Bach, Thien Quang, Thu Le, Kim Lien, Xuan Khanh, Tuy Lai, Quan Son and so forth.
Air travelers flying into Hanoi will need to go through Noi Bai International Airport, about 40 minutes drive from the Hanoi city center. Located in Soc Son District about 28 miles north of Hanoi's city center, Noi Bai lies about 40 minutes' taxi ride from the Old Quarter. Travelers exiting from Noi Bai Airport can take the bus, minibus, taxi, or hotel airport transfer to Hanoi city proper. Buses and minibusses cost the least but take up the most waiting or travel time. Taxis are your most expensive option but can get you to town the fastest, assuming you can navigate your way around the touts and scammers in the arrivals area.
You can get around Hanoi by walking, taking taxis, cyclo, or motorcycle taxis, renting a scooter, or riding a bicycle.
Hanoi's taxis have meters, but not all drivers like to use them. Working meters cost about VND10,000 to VND15,000 for the first two kilometers, then about VND8,000 per succeeding kilometer.
The trouble with taking a taxi is not all of them are well-versed in English, and some will try to impose a flat rate for your trip instead of relying on the meter. Even when they use the meter, some of them will have defective meters that run too fast!
If hailing a taxi in Hanoi, look for one of these reputable taxis, instead of just any taxi that passes your way. You can also call them to get a taxi sent to your location. The taxis in this list are slightly less likely to try to rip you off: Hanoi Taxi, Mai Linh Taxi, Taxi CP. The language gap is a big problem when getting around in Hanoi, as Vietnamese is a tonal language that adds dots and squiggles to Latin characters that change their pronunciation entirely! So don't try to tell the driver where you want to go; show him a paper or card that has the address in writing. (Those calling cards at your hotel front desk? Grab a handful and use them for your trips.) Taxi drivers in Hanoi are also loath to give back change. If this is a big deal for you, bring smaller bills to pay the exact change.
Cyclo are Hanoi's bicycle rickshaws. Passengers ride in the front cab, while the driver sits behind the passenger. Cyclo cabs are made for two passengers and are ideal for exploring short distances within Hanoi's city center. Ride them only if you're in no hurry, and if you don't mind the fright of seeing Hanoi's traffic whiz right in front of you.
A ride in a cyclo should cost you about VND 100,000 (about $5) for an hour's ride. They may ask for more at the outset, but you're encouraged to haggle the price down. Agree on the price up front before boarding. Don't be surprised if the cyclo driver will try to charge you more as soon as you get down. Pay the price you agreed at the outset, and be firm about it - however, do tip him for his services, as he's pedaled your entire body weight for the past hour. Have the correct change ready, as cyclo drivers (like their taxi counterparts) hate to give back change.
Hanoi's motorcycle taxis can be translated to "hug vehicle", and that's what it amounts to: you ride pillion on the motorcycle and hug the driver from behind, hanging on for dear life as the both of you whiz through the city's traffic. You'll find them mainly around street corners; you can tell them by their green pith helmets. The price should be negotiable and will depend on the distance you wish to travel. For every kilometer, about VND 10,000-15,000 (about fifty to seventy cents) is a fair amount.
Negotiate the rate before boarding, and try to pay exact change as much as possible. Make sure your motorcycle taxi has a spare helmet; don't get on if they lack this essential piece of equipment! Planning to travel over 2 miles to your destination? Get a taxi instead, it's more practical, and safer too.
Renting a scooter may be an option if you want a little more flexibility to your travel around Hanoi. Many guesthouses or hotels can get their guests a motorbike to rent for about $5 per day. Take note that you'll need to get a local driving license before you can rent a motorbike or a car in Vietnam: visit the Hanoi Department of Public Works and Transportation to get one. Also, do note that newbies shouldn't attempt Hanoi's chaotic traffic; the rules of the road do not exist along the city's streets, and a shaky new driver will only end up injured or worse.
Riding a bicycle through Hanoi is not for the weak-kneed; traffic rules fly out the window as soon as you hit the road, and accidents are a definite possibility. Bicyclists must also contend with hot, humid weather between April to August. If none of these faze you, then pedal on; many hotels in Hanoi offer bike rental services, often going for as low as $1 a day.
